{"tossups": [{"question": "A passenger on this man\u2019s second expedition, Bristol merchant William Weston, later led his own voyage further south to the Hudson Strait. A passenger on this man\u2019s third voyage, an Augustinian friar named Giovanni Antonio de Carbonariis, may have founded the first Catholic mission in North America. This man\u2019s voyage to continental North America was likely the first by a European since Leif Erikson\u2019s voyage to Vinland. For the point, name this Italian explorer commissioned to go to the New World by the British.", "answer": "John<b> Cabot</b> (accept Giovanni<b> Caboto</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "A eunuch who served this dynasty named Zhao Gao acted as its<em> de facto</em> ruler in the third century BC. Jing Ke [kuh] nearly assassinated a ruler of this dynasty by concealing a dagger inside a map scroll. This dynasty\u2019s Legalist minister, Li Si, ordered the burning of many Confucian and political texts. One king of this dynasty was buried with thousands of statues after dying in an attempt to become immortal. For the point, name this first dynasty of a unified China.", "answer": "<b> Qin</b> [chin] dynasty", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This artist set Guinness World Records for Most successful concert series, Highest grossing concert film for<em> This Is It</em>, and Youngest vocalist to top the U.S. singles chart. In 1992, this artist started a foundation that sent money to children affected by war, poverty, and disease, named \u201cHeal the World\u201dafter a hit song on his<em> Dangerous</em> album. For the point, name this writer of hits such as \u201cBeat It\u201d and\u201cThriller,\u201d known worldwide as the \u201cKing of Pop.\u201d", "answer": "Michael<b> Jackson</b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "After a bloody conflict over the client kingdom of Iberia, this ruler and Khosrow I signed an eternal peace. This ruler\u2019s wife convinced him not to flee the unrest caused by the Greens and Blues during the Nika Riot. This man sent Belisarius to conquer the Vandalic Kingdom in an attempt to recreate the Roman Empire. For the point, name this Eastern Orthodox saint, husband of the actress Theodora, and Byzantine Emperor.", "answer": "<b> Justinian</b> the Great (or<b> Justinian</b> I)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "Citizens from this city chose Piero Soderini to succeed a priest who prophesied the arrival of a \u201cCyrus of the north\u201d to reform the Church. Piero the Unfortunate was deposed as ruler of this city, after which Girolamo Savonarola organized the \u201cBonfire of the Vanities.\u201d Lorenzo the Maginificent patronized artists like Michelangelo and Botticelli while ruling this city. For the point, name this Italian city which was led by the Medici family during the Renaissance.", "answer": "<b> Florence</b> (accept<b> Firenze</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This ethnolinguistic group\u2019s cultural phenomenon known as \u201cghost sickness\u201d is symbolized in Paul Gauguin\u2019s painting<em> Spirit of the Dead Watching</em>. A World War Two manual instructs soldiers to use this people\u2019s tradition of following bird migration patterns to survive the open ocean. Thor Heyerdahl used the <em>Kon-Tiki</em> raft to prove these people could traverse the Pacific Ocean and reach South America. For the point, name this ethnolinguistic group of the islands of Tonga, Samoa, Tuvalu, and a French dependency named for them.", "answer": "<b> Polynesian</b>s (prompt on Tahitians and other specific Polynesian groups)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "Insults directed at this hero led to the deaths of Plexippus and Toxeus. At Pelias\u2019s funeral games, this hero defeated the father of Achilles in a wrestling match. This hero was raised by bears after being abandoned on a mountainside by Iasus. Meleager awarded this hero the hide of the Calydonian Boar after she drew first blood. For the point, name this Greek huntress who lost to Hippomenes in a footrace after being distracted by some golden apples.", "answer": "<b> Atalanta</b>", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {}, {"question": "Description acceptable. One early story about this concept was Max Beerbohm\u201ds \u201cEnoch Soames: A Memory of the Eighteen-Nineties,\u201d in which the title character accomplishes this action via a deal with the devil. The concept of a machine to accomplish this action was introduced in Edward Page Mitchell\u2019s\u201cThe Clock that Went Backward.\u201d H.G. Wells popularized this concept in a story about a Traveller who encounters Morlocks and Eloi in the fourth dimension. For the point, what is this fictional concept, in which a character visits the past or future?", "answer": "<b> Time travel</b> (accept descriptions of<b> travel</b>ing in<b> time</b>)", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Short Fiction"}, {"question": "The capture of this city by the Hundred Thousand Sons of Saint Louis movement guaranteed the restoration of a Bourbon monarch. In this city, ETA separatists placed a bomb in a tunnel beneath where Prime Minister Luis Carrero Blanco was driving, blowing his car 60 feet in the air in a 1973 assassination. This capital city is the location of the crowning of Juan Carlos I, who was personally chosen to succeed Francisco Franco as leader of the nation. For the point, name this capital city of Spain.", "answer": "<b> Madrid</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This composer included simple keyboard pieces in a 1725 \u201cNotebook\u201d for his wife, and his chorales formed the basis for modern counterpoint rules. In 1722, this composer produced the first major collection of keyboard pieces in all 24 keys, and Glenn Gould made his debut with a recording of this composer\u2019s <em>Goldberg Variations</em>. For the point, identify this Baroque composer of<em> The Well-Tempered Clavier</em> and the <em>Brandenburg Concertos</em>.", "answer": "<b> J</b>ohann<b> S</b>ebastian<b> Bach</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "Tony Shafrazi spray-painted the words \u201cKILL LIES ALL\u201d onto this painting to protest the My Lai massacre. The artist of this painting loaned it to the Museum of Modern Art on the condition that it would be shipped to Spain once democracy had been re-established. This painting is entirely in greyscale, and it depicts a horse writhing in pain at its center. For the point, name this anti-war painting by Pablo Picasso that depicts the bombing of a Basque town.", "answer": "<em><b> Guernica</b></em>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "This ruler put an end to the Crimean War and established local governments known as zemstvos. This ruler was also responsible for selling part of his country to the United States. After numerous attempts, this ruler was finally assassinated in 1881 by a member of the People\u2019s Will, after which many of his reforms were reversed. One of this ruler\u2019s major reforms earned him the nickname \u201cthe Liberator.\u201dFor the point, name this Tsar who freed Russia\u2019s serfs and sold Alaska to the United States.", "answer": "<b> Alexander II</b> (accept<b> Alexander the Liberator</b> before it is mentioned)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A period of hyperinflation during this man\u2019s regime led to a coup orchestrated by the Derg and the executions of \u201cBloody Saturday.\u201d This man, crowned the \u201cNegusa Negast\u201d or \u201cKing of Kings,\u201d faced a two pronged invasion by Italy from Somaliland and Eritrea, leading to his exile in the UK. In a 1967 CBC interview with Bill McNeil, this monarch denied his divinity, although some people continued to view him as the messiah who would lead Africa to freedom. For the point, name this last emperor of the Solomonic Dynasty, an Ethiopian monarch and Rastafarian deity.", "answer": "<b> Haile Selassie</b> I (accept Ras<b> Tafari</b> or Lij Tafari<b> Makonnen</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "In this city, Jorge Selaron\u2019s mosaics decorate a 215-step staircase called the Escanderia Selaron. The first Europeans in the region of this city landed at Guanabara Bay in 1502 and were part of the fleet of Pedro \u00b4Alvarez Cabral. This city was its nation\u2019s capital from 1763 until Juscelino Kubutschek had a new capital built in 1960. The<em> Christ the Redeemer</em> statue overlooks, for the point, what city, the second-most populous after S\u02dcao Paulo in Brazil?", "answer": "<b> Rio</b> de Janeiro", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {}, {"question": "For the point, name this nation with the cities of The Hague and Amsterdam.", "answer": "Kingdom of the<b> Netherlands</b> (accept<b> Dutch</b> Republic or<b> United Provinces</b> of the <b>Netherlands</b>) (30) This tribe\u2019s \u201cFreedmen\u201d were barred from citizenship by Principal Chief Wilma Mankiller. These people prevailed in a Supreme Court case against Samuel Austin Worcester. Elias Boudinot published the <em>Phoenix</em> newspaper in this tribe\u2019s syllabary. This group was led by John Ross after the Treaty of New Echota forced them to relocate from Georgia. For the point, name this Native American tribe who were forced west along the Trail of Tears. ANSWER:<b> Cherokee</b> (accept<b> Aniyunwiya</b> or<b> Tsalagi</b>) <b>Extra Question</b> Only read if moderator botches a question.", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "General Robert Gu\u00b4e\u00a8\u0131 [GAY-ee] seized power in this nation for nine months but eventually lost in an election to the only opposition leader allowed, Laurent Gbagbo [BAHG-boh]. Explorer Louis Gustave Binger [banh-zhay] ended an expedition in this modern day country\u2019s settlement of Grand Bassam. In early European sources, this place was also called \u201cThe Coast of Teeth.\u201d For the point, name this modern day nation first governed by F\u00b4elix Houphou\u00a8et-Boigny [oo-fway bwahn-yee] from the capital Yamoussoukro", "answer": "Republic of<b> Cote d\u2019Ivoire</b> (accept<b> Ivory Coast</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}], "bonuses": []}